Finding Aid for the Byron McAfee Papers LSC.0339
UCLA Library Special Collections
- II. Research papers, 1768-1964.; 16 boxes.
  - IID. Nahua history and culture, 1857-1964.; (3 boxes).
    - Valeriano, Antonio de. Dialogue of the Apparition of the Virgin of Guadalupe, ca. 1935.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 10)
      Nahuatl play, translated to English by John Hubert Cornyn. Typescript.
    - Van Zantwijk, Rodolfo. Los indigenas de Milpa Alta, 1959.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 11)
      Transcription and translation of Nahuatl text to Spanish. Bound typescript.
    - Vega, Luis Lazo de la. Nican Mopohua, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 12)
      Nahuatl transcription from published source, on the apparition of the Virgin of Guadalupe. Bound typescript.
    - Versos de la danza de la gran Conquista, entrada de Don Fernando Cortes, Marquez del Valle, Español vencedor, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 13)
      A collection of verses in Nahuatl. Typescript.
    - Zazanillatolli. Fabulas de Esopo, ca. 1895.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 14)
      Manuscript and typescript on Celtatecalt. See also Cortes, Agustin Hunt.
    - Sacrifice of Issac (El Nacimiento de Izac) (folder 1 of 3), ca. 1932.; 5 items. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Assorted copies and translations. Bound typescripts.
    - Sacrifice of Issac (El Nacimiento de Izac) (folder 2 of 3), ca.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Spanish translation from Nahuatl by Chimalpopoca, signed by John Hubert Cornyn. Typescript.
    - Sacrifice of Issac (El Nacimiento de Izac) (folder 3 of 3), ca. 1950.; 8 items. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Study of the Nahuatl language, as used in the transcription of an earlier text. Includes introduction. Bound typescripts.
    - La Sociedad Pro-Lengua Nahuatl Mariano Jacobo Rojas, 1942.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Nahuatl language center information, and some poetry. 10 loose typescript leaves.
    - Teomahuizotl (Catholic Mass), 1940-1942.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Spanish to Nahuatl language transcription and translation of mass and commandments in variants of the Nahuatl language, including Hacienda de Camotipan, Veracruz (also known as Hacienda de Santa Teresa, in Municipio de Chicontepec, Veracruz). Includes a version in Texcoco variant of the Nahuatl mass compiled by Sr. Montaño, as well as Puebla variant and Tepoztaln Morelos; translation of ten commandments from Nahuatl to Spanish; and gospel according to St. John in Nahuatl. Loose typescript leaves.
    - Tlatolpepechtli, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Typescript Nahuatl version of a Huehuetlatolli play, possibly from the 16th century. Corrections in Spanish.
    - Tlaxcalteca songs, ca. 1935.; 2 items. (Box 17, Folder 8)
      Transcription of Tlaxcalteca songs in Nahuatl, with extensive holograph annotations in English. Map of native communities in North Central Mexico on a separate leaf.
    - Tohueitlatocatzine, 1866.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Photostat of an invitation to attend a recital of texts in Nahuatl.
  - IIE. Miscellaneous, 1768-1953.; (2 boxes).
    Assorted research papers and publications reflecting McAfee's interests in Mexican culture, medicine and politics, including articles and commentary on the expropriation of petroleum under President Lazaro Cardenas. Materials are arranged alphabetacally by folder title. See box 12 for oversize articles from El semanario ilustrado on Santo Tomas (Saint Thomas)
    - Almada, Agustin Aguiar. Newspaper articles, 1938 November 12.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Series of essays from the weekly review HOY, responding to published articles on petroleum expropriation by the Mexican government. Typescript, with magazine clippings mounted on the leaves.
    - Catholic Church. Officia sanctorum in breviario romano., 1768.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 10)
      Title page and index to an early Mexican imprint. Title page features a printer's ornament of the Virgin de Guadalupe, and other decorations. (Medina 5219).
    - El Distrito Federal de la República Mexicana es un lugar á propósito para la prevencion y curacion de la tuberculosis, 1891.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 11)
      Published article from El estudio on establishing a center for the study and treatment of tuberculosis in Mexico City.
    - Filiación del Capitán Juan de la Tovilla, 1907.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 12)
      Extracto del libro de Blasones de la familia Tovilla, de San Cristobal Las Casas. Published excerpt from an unidentified source on the history of the Tovilla family in Chiapas and Guatemala.
    - Flores, Leodegario. Nuestra salutacion, 1953 May 31.; 2 items. (Box 18, Folder 13)
      Speech on teaching Nahuatl in schools, such as the Escuela Normal Poblana and the Sociedad Pro-Lengua Nahuatl, "Mariano Jacobo Rojas." Typescript of a related document, in Nahuatl and English. Mexico City, Delegacion Cuauhtemoc.
    - Goméz de Orozco, Federico. La tipografía colonial mexicana, ca. 1939.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 14)
      On printing in colonial Mexico. Published in Mexico, by Universidad Nacional. No. 2 in a series on cuadernos de arte.
    - Haba del Calabar, ca. 1890.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 15)
      Published article on Haba del Calabar.
    - Llorona, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 16)
      Handwritten penciled notes in Nahuatl, about Llorona, Miahuatlan, Puebla. On the reverse side of the leaves, struck through with pencil, is typewritten text in a native language of Chiapas. 6 leaves.
    - Louvrier, F. Avant-projet d'utilisation, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 17)
      Report on the Amacuzac River, and its potential as a source for an energy generation plant. Text in French. Bound typescript.
    - Lucio, Rafael and Ignacio Alvarado. Opúsculo sobre el mal de San Lázaro ó elefantiasis de los griegos, 1889.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 18)
      Medical study on elephantiasis, in Spanish. Published in Mexico, by the Ofisina tip. de la Secretaría de Fomento.
    - Barlow, Robert. Lista de micropelicula, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Barlow's microfilm inventory. Typescript.
    - Botanical species of Mexico, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Alphabetical catalog of descriptions for plant species found in Mexico. Unknown author, text in Spanish. Bound typescript.
    - Bravo, Izquierdo Aurelio. The petroleum debt, 1939 January 14.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Essay from the weekly review HOY. Critical article on the expropriation of petroleum deposits by the Mexican government. Typescript, with magazine clippings mounted on the leaves.
    - Cabrera, Luis. The petroleum problem, 1938 July 30.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Essay from the weekly review HOY, responding to published articles on petroleum expropriation by the Mexican government. Also entitled "El problema del petroleo: las soluciones imposibles." Typescript, with magazine clippings mounted on the leaves.
    - Cárdenas, Lazaro. Mensaje del C. Presidente de la Republica, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Transcription and Nahuatl translation of a presidential speech, by Ezequiel Linares. Typescript, 4 leaves.
    - Carmona y Valle, Manuel María. Anomalías de la refracción, 1889.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Tesis para el concurso á la plaza de adjunto á la Catedra de clínica externa de la Escuela de medicina de México. Published in Mexico, by the Oficina tip. de la Secretaría de Fomento.
    - Carmona y Valle, Manuel María. Mecanismo de la acomodación, 1889.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Medical essay in Spanish. Published in Mexico, by the Oficina tip. de la Secretaría de Fomento.
    - Carrasco, J. Bibiano. Estudio de las aguas de Axocopan (Distrito de Atlixco Estado de Puebla), 1889.; 1 item. (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Study on the water of Axocopan, in the Atlixco County, in the state of Puebla. Published in Mexico, by the Oficina tip. de la Secretaría de Fomento.
    - Mallén, Rafael. Nueva teoría estática de las construcciones, 1907.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 1)
      "De los momentos virtuales," y sistema de construcciones en Cemento Armado "El Fénix." Published article about construction technologies.
    - Mendieta y Nuñez, L. El problema agrario de Mexico, ca. 1936.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Published article on agrarian problems in the valley of Teotihuacan, from an unidentified source. Includes index and bibliographical references.
    - Monografías Mexicanas de Materia Médica, 1890-1897.; 5 items. (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Tésis inagurales y de concurso de la Escuela Nacional de Medicina de Mexico. Acopiadas y reproducidas for El estudio. Published in Mexico, by the Ofisina tip. de la Secretaría de fomento.
    - Primer congreso médico de la isla de Cuba, 1890.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Reseña publicada por la Crónica médico-quirúrgica de la Habana. Published in Mexico, by the Ofisina tip. de la Secretaría de fomento.
    - Rabasa, Oscar. Compensation for the petroleum expropriation, 1938 December 17.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Essay from the weekly review HOY, responding to published articles on petroleum expropriation by the Mexican government. Typescript, with magazine clippings mounted on the leaves.
    - Rivera, Maria del Pilar, ca. 1930.; 2 items. (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Stories and a poem about Maria del Pilar Rivera, sister of Mexican muralist Diego Rivera. Narrative entitled "Maria del Pilar, de la vida/anecdotas del famoso Pintor Diego Rivera"; poem entitled "En horas de tristeza." Typescript, 8 leaves.
    - Romero Flores, Jesús. Documentos para la biografía del historiador Clavijero, 1945.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 7)
      Includes copies of correspondence by Francesco Saverio Clavigero (1731- 1787), an 18th century historian of Mexico. Published in Mexico, by the Secretaria de Educacion Publica. Reprint of an article from the Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia. Signed by the author.
    - Sbengal, Duna (?). La noche llegó dos veces, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 8)
      Manuscript for a work of fiction, possibly a novel. Incomplete; beginning leaves badly damaged. Typescript.
    - Serrano, Rafael. Fragmentos de psiquiatría óptica, 1890.; 1 item. (Box 19, Folder 9)
      Tésis inaugural, Facultad de medicina de Puebla 1884. Published in Mexico, by the Ofisina tip. de la Secretaría de fomento.
- III. Manuscripts, 1553-1864.; 1 box.
  The manuscripts include Nahuatl and Spanish-language testaments, deeds, petitions, complaints, and contracts for the sale of land from the areas of Metepec, Azcapotzalco, Tlaxcala and Coyoacan. They have been filed in the order in which they were found in Byron McAfee's scrapbook. Preliminary descriptions of the items were created in the early 1990s by Barry Sell; Xóchitl M. Flores-Marcial contributed additional descriptive data while completing her 2005 inventory, and these descriptions were incorporated into the finding aid. Descriptions for the manuscripts that were transcribed and translated in Beyond the Codices: The Nahua View of Colonial Mexico (ed. and trans. by Arthur J.O. Anderson, Frances Berdan and James Lockhart, University of California Press, 1976) include a citation to the page on which they appear in that publication.
  - [Testament of Maria Teresa and Estevan Domingo], Santa Cruz, Tianguistenco, 1783 July 28.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    1 bifolium: paper; 212 x 154 mm. Will of Estevan Domingo and his wife (possibly widow), Maria Teresa. Signed by Simon Narcisco b Allino, notary. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Petition against Fray Juan de Vizcarre], Guaxicori and Guadalajara, 1652 April-May.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 10)
    31 leaves: paper; 320 x 215 mm. Assorted documents "contra el Pe Fr Juan de Vizcarre, guardian del convente de San Francisco" (f. 1r). Includes petitions, letters, and testimony of Sebastian Garcia against Vizcarre. Second half of manuscript is comprised of copies of documents from civil and ecclesiastical authorities, including the execution of his sentence and exile from the parish. Final leaf is unrelated to the case, and is an edict of the Governor and alcaldes of Atzapotzalco, 1569 January 14. Text in Nahuatl, with some Spanish translations.
  - [Complaint against the vicar of Tonelan], Guadalajara, 1656 December 29.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 11)
    1 leaf: paper; 155 x 208 mm. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1747 October 7, 1767 July 1.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 12)
    2 leaves: paper; 305 x 215 mm. Purchase of land by Doña Gertrudis Perez de Bustamante from Doña Antonia, her husband Miguel Martinez de Miranda, and their son, Julian Roman Martinez de Miranda. Leaf 2 is a confirmation of the sale of the land on 1767 July 1 from Gertrudis to Agustina Veronica of Chalco. Stamp of King Philip V. Text in Nahuatl and Spanish.
  - [Notification of penalties], Azcapotzalco, 1703 July 5.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 13)
    1 leaf: paper; 310 x 215 mm. Edict by the council of Azcapotzalco on the penalties of non-compliance regarding land agreements. Specifically concerns Andrés González and his lands, in the district of San Simón. Stamp of King Philip V. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson 96)
  - [Testament of Pedro San Juan], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1733 March 9.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 14)
    1 leaf; paper; 210 x 153 mm. Includes instructions for mass and the division of property. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1785 June 19.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 15)
    1 leaf: paper; 210 x 192 mm. Purchase or deed of land to Hilario de San Juan from his aunt, Josepha Teresa. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Miguel Jerónimo], Metepec, 1795 December 9.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 16)
    1 bifolium: paper; 312 x 210 mm. Final will and testament. Contains instructions for burial, and directions for the division of his land and property. Signed by witnesses and a notary. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 72)
  - [Letter, council of Tzacualco to council of San Felipe], San Felipe, 1629 October 20.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 17)
    1 bifolium: paper; 312 x 218 mm. Letter regarding arrangements for a marriage. Signed by several witnesses. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 196)
  - [Preface to a testament], origin unknown, [17--].; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 18)
    1 leaf: 305 x 210 mm. Presumed to be a preface to a testament, with extensive praise of the Virgin. Includes a marginal note, in Spanish, regarding a contract for renting land between Ilario Carrillo and Diego Joseph De Lares. Difficult cursive hand. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Baptismal certificate], Havana, Cuba, 1864 October 14.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 19)
    1 leaf: 307 x 212 mm. Formal acknowledgement of the legitimate birth of Maria Teresa Antonia Dominga Diega de Jesus. Stamp and embossed seal at top of leaf. Text in Spanish.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Azcapotzalco, 1742 February 21.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    1 bifolium: paper; 411 x 214 mm. Purchase of land by Don Juan Soriano, Spaniard, from Juan de la Cruz, of San Lucas Atenco, and Maria Simona of San Sebastian. Signed by Antonio Bilibaldo Flores, notary. Stamp of King Philip V on recto and verso. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Juan Baes, et. al], San Juan Ixtenco, Tlaxcala, 1733 February 10-1758 July 8.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 20)
    8 leaves: paper; 305 x 215 mm. Extract of the testament of Juan Baes, and related documents comprised of individual bifolia (dated 1733 to 1758) sewn together. Manuscripts relate to a piece of land left to his brother, Jose Baes, with an imposition for masses on the land. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land, et. al], San Felipe Santiago, Atzcapotzalco Tianguistenco, 1726 March 5.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 21)
    6 leaves: paper; 312 x 215 mm. Series of manuscripts relating to various transfers of ownership for a piece of land. First document is a sales contract involving don Felipe Felisiano and his wife Pasquala Maria, and members of their family. The land was located in the barrio Santo Domingo, and the seller was don Antonio de Santiago and his wife, Doña Maria Francisca. Remaining documents date from 1738, when the land in question was sold to Bartolome Vargas and his family. Signatures of witnesses throughout. Leaves 5 and 6 are blank; all leaves bear the stamp of King Philip V. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Joachin Flores], Coyoacan, 1602 April 23.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 22)
    1 bifolium: paper; 314 x 218 mm. Flores was a resident of Santo Domingo Pixcohuac. Will includes instructions for mass and burial, and directions for the division of property. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Catalina Papan], Tehuitzco, 1571 December 10.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 23)
    1 bifolium: paper; 316 x 216 mm. Will of a woman dying from "cocoliztli," or smallpox. Will includes a prayer, instructions for mass and burial, and directions regarding her house and division of property. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Account summary for Diego Francisco], San Mateo, Huitzilopochco, [15--?].; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 24)
    1 leaf: paper; 313 x 217 mm. Account of money received by Diego Francisco from various people. Huitzilopochco is modern-day Churubusco. See also MS 32. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Tomas Feliciano], Omaxacuehuecalco, 1579 April 29.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 25)
    2 leaves: paper; 315 x 217 mm. Final will and testament, with instructions for mass, burial, and the division of property. Signed by Joseph Jacabo, scribe. Second leaf is a record of Lorenco de la Assumpción receiving 6 pesos from Francisco de Santo Domingo, for the two masses ordered in the will. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Estate summary for Juana and Gabriel Rafael], Coyoacan?, ca. 1632.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 26)
    1 bifolium: paper; 305 x 210 mm. Summary statement, possibly by an executor, for Juana (d. 1629 March 21) and her husband, Gabriel Rafael (d. ca. 1630). Includes the cost of their masses and settlement of property. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 76)
  - [Testament of Ana Lucia], San Geronimo, Zacamahcuexpa, 1622 January 13.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 27)
    1 bifolium: paper; 217 x 154 mm. Woman's will. Signed by Juan Gaspar, scribe. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for transfer of land], Tlalxopa, 1579 January 21.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 28)
    1 leaf: paper ;157 x 216 mm. Documents a transfer of land between Maria Ana and Juana Helna [Helena] to Francisco Leon Carvajal. Includes an map-like drawing of the property in ink, "cedula del pedazo de tierra de Elena."
  - [Contract for transfer of land], Xochac Coyoacan, 1579 January 21.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 29)
    1 leaf: paper; 159 x 217 mm. Transfer of land to Francisco Leon Carvajal from Maria. Includes a map-like drawing of the property in ink, "cedula del pedazo de tierra que toque con la bieja de Xochac." Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land, et. al], Azcapotzalco, 1738 December 15.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    3 leaves: paper; 311 x 210 mm. Purchase of land by Don Antonio Gonzalez, a Spaniard, from Salvador Francisco and his wife, Maria de la Concepción of San Francisco Tzapotla, and Josef de Santiago and his wife Rosa Maria of San Lucas Atenco. Includes acts of investigation, confirmation, and possession. Also includes part of a will for Esteban Diego of San Domingo Huexotitlan. Don Juan Soriano serves as apoderado for Gonzalez Tercero. Signed by Antonio Bilibaldo Flores, notary. Stamp of King Philip V on f. 1r. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 100)
  - [Statement of Maria Ana], Tetzala Purificacion, 1622 October 9.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 30)
    1 leaf: paper; 200 x 150 mm. Statement taken near time of death. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for transfer of land], Tlalxopa, Coyohuacan, 1579 January 21.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 31)
    1 leaf: paper; 157 x 218 mm. Transfer of land from Miguel de Santiago to Francisco de Leon Carvajal. Includes a map-like drawing of the property in ink, "cedula del pedazo de tierra que me dio lorenzo y lo di a la biexa de Xochac en truxe que de otro que ella me troco." Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Account summary for Diego Francisco], San Matheo, Huitzilopochco, [15--?].; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 32)
    1 leaf: paper; 215 x 156 mm. Continuation of accounts for Diego Francisco, dealing with zapotes. See also MS 24. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Request for payment and receipt], Mexico, 1579 June 13.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 33)
    1 leaf: paper; 157 x 220 mm. Involves a debt of Diego Perez de Zamora and Juan Alonso Altamirano to pay 200 pesos in principal to Melchor de Morales. Demand issued by Lic. Santiago de Vera. Text in Spanish.
  - [Contract for transfer of land], Tlalxopa, 1579 January 21.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 34)
    1 leaf: paper; 160 x 215 mm. Land transfer from Lorenzo Perez to Francisco de Leon Carvajal. Includes a map-like drawing of the property in ink, "cedula de Lorenzo, y este pedazo di a la bieja." Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Receipt of debt], origin unknown, 1588 May 10.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 35)
    1 leaf: paper; 318 x 220 mm. Receipt of a debt from Don Diego de San Francisco to Pierres de Portugal. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Donations to the church of San Juan Bautista], Coyoacan, 1575 June-August.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 36)
    1 leaf: paper; 315 x 215 mm. Appears to be a page from the notary register of Tomás Feliciano. Includes records for two gifts of land to the church; one by Juan Alvar and his wife, Ana Elvilla of Axolco, the other from Baltaser Esteban and his wife, Isabel, of Tlalxopa. Donations were received by Fray Francisco de Loysa. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 112)
  - [Testament of Don Juan de Guzmán], Coyoacan, 1622 June 12.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 37)
    1 bifolium: paper; 306 x 214 mm. Final will and testament, containing a prayer, burial instructions, and directions for the sale and division of his orchards and property. Signed by Fray Alonso de Paredes, witness. (Anderson, 64)
  - [Donation to the church of San Juan Bautista], Coyocan, 1621 August 7.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 38)
    1 leaf: paper; 310 x 211 mm. Documentation of a gift of land to the church. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Juan Fabián], San Bartolomé Atenco, 1617 August 1.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 39)
    1 bifolium: paper; 313 x 210 mm. Final will and testament, containing a prayer, bell-ringing and mass instructions, and directions for the complex division of his property, land, and debts. Signed by witnesses. Annotation in a separate hand on recto, signed by Fray Juan de Peralta, confirming the mass was celebrated as requested. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 58)
  - [Testament of Angelina], San Simón Pochtlan, 1695 August 16.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    1 leaf: paper; 315 x 220 mm. Final will and testament. Contains instructions for mass, and the division of land and property among her grandchildren and son-in-law. Signed by notary and witnesses. Manuscript has been conserved to stabilize the paper. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 68)
  - [Municipal grant of land to Joaquín Flores], Coyoacan, 1575.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 40)
    1 leaf: paper; 313 x 217 mm. Complete date is missing due to a tear in the upper right corner. Grant is made by the village council of Coyoacan to Joaquín Flores of Atleputzco before Agustín de Galicia, notary. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson 94)
  - [Contract for sale of land], Coyoacan, 1573 February.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 41)
    1 leaf: paper; 318 x 215 mm. Complete date is missing due to a tear in the upper right corner. Contract between Pedro de Santiago and Don Toribio Silvestre, and Pedro Pierres de Portugal, a Spaniard. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson 98)
  - [Petition by the people of Coatlan de Puertos Abaxo], Coatlan, 1637 July 1.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 42)